Guide to the Bosanka Evosevic Papers, 1974-1979 AIS.1978.23
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Bosanka Evosevic Papers
1974-1979
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Evosevic, Bosanka
AIS.1978.23
1.25 Linear Feet
Material on the International Women's Year Conference, Pittsburgh and Allegheny County schools/education, affirmative action, ERA, and women's rights.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Bosanka Evosevic Papers, 1974-1979, AIS.1978.23, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Biography
According to her Pittsburgh Post-Gazette obituary, Bosanka Evosevic was an active civic leader in Pittsburgh until her death on October 18, 1982. She was the first Pittsburgher to serve in the Peace Corps, was a retired vice principal of South High School on the South Side (where she was a life long resident), and co-owned Sarah's Restaurant on Tenth Street with her mother.
Ms. Evosevic was a member of the National Organization for Women (NOW) and the first members of NOW in Pittsburgh. She was active in women's studies at the University of Pittsburgh, Duquesne University, and Community College of Allegheny County. She was a former member of the Human Relations Commission; the South Side Community Council; the Pittsburgh History & Landmarks Foundation; and the city's Bicentennial Commission. She hosted the television program "Faith in Today's World."
Ms. Evosevic served as a delegate to the National Women's Conference hosted by the National Commission on the Observance of International Women's Year. She also was a member of the Coordinating Committee for Pennsylvania.
For more information on Ms. Evosevic, please refer to her obituary found in the University Archives Information Files.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains material on the International Women's Year Conference, Pittsburgh and Allegheny County schools/education, affirmative action, the equal rights amendment (ERA), and women's rights.
Women; Education; Personal papers; Social action; Women's rights -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Women's rights -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Affirmative action programs in education -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Affirmative action programs in education -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Education -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Education -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Public schools -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Public schools -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Allegheny County (Pa.); Pittsburgh (Pa.); Evosevic, Bosanka
- International Women's Year Commission
  - Rules and Regulations (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Public Relations - News Releases, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Letters, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Delegate Letters (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memorabilia: ERA Pins and Signs (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - National Women's Conference - Daily Bulletins No. 1 and 3, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - List of Resolutions adopted at Houston Conference, November 18-21, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Pennsylvania Coordinating Committee - Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Pennsylvania Coordinating Committee - Executive Committee - Minutes, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Pennsylvania Coordinating Committee - Memorandum, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Pennsylvania Delegation/WomanKind, National Organization for Women -- Memorandum, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Report of the Pennsylvania Delegation to the National Women's Conference, October 10, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - National Commission on the Observance of International Women's Year, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - National Women's Conference, Literature - Programs: "American Women on the Move;" "Woman: 1977, The Status of American Women;" Proposed National Plan of Action; Job Discrimination Handbook (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - WomanKind - Pennsylvania Women's Meeting - Memorabilia, June 24-26, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Pennsylvania Women's Caucus - State Convention Pamphlet, 1974, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Affirmative Action - Literature, National Organization for Women Newsletters, KNOW Catalogue, Newspaper Articles, National Congress of Neighborhood Women Newsletters, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- ERA - Pamphlets: "The ERA: What does it mean to you?", "ERA Special" (Box 2, Folder 2)
- National Women's Political Caucus: "We Have A Lot to Win", July 13-15, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Role of Women (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Scope and Content Notes
  "The 1972 Virginia Slims American Women's Opinion Poll;" "Women's Resource Booklet: The Ford Foundation's Program in the Changing Role of Women;" "The Commission on the Status and Needs of Women at CMU;" articles and clippings on women and equal rights.
- Schools/Education
  - Keystone Oaks School District, Allegheny County - Applications and Information (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Penn Hills School District - Applications, Information, and Affirmative Action Procedures, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Armstrong School District - Applications, Information, Collective Bargaining Agreement (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - North Allegheny Schools - Applications, Information, Collective Bargaining Agreement (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Upper St. Clair Township School District - Personnel Staffing Policies, "Child Service Demonstration Center for Students with Learning Disabilities (CSDC)" Information (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 2)
    "Collective Bargaining Agreement between the Pittsburgh Board of Public Education and the Pittsburgh Federation of Teachers, 1972-1975;" "Collective Bargaining Agreement between the Upper St. Clair Education Association and the Board of Education of the School District of the Township of Upper St. Clair, 1973-1977;" Open the Door to a Teaching Career in Upper St. Clair;" Program - Tri-State Area School Study Council - School Board Institute, March 26, 1975; East Stroudsburg State College - Department of Professional Physical Education: Guidelines; Upper St. Clair Schools, Newsletter, May-June 1975; North Allegheny School District, Teachers Handbook-Grade K-12, 1974-1975; Tri-State Area School Study Council: Memo to Board Members, October 1974 and January 1975, and Superintendents Brief, April 1974, May 1974, December 1974, and May 1975; Report: The Discussion Draft in the Pittsburgh Schools, written by the Government Study Commission, City of Pittsburgh, November 29, 1973; "Two Special Projects: The Colfax and Acmetonia Elementary Schools in Allegheny Valley School District" by the Allegheny Valley School Authority and Board (booklet); "Pittsburgh Public Schools: System-Wide Staff Meeting, A Telecast via WQED, Channel 13," Booklet, September 1, 1977; "Pittsburgh Public Schools Membership Report as of October 1, 1973," prepared by Statistics office; North Allegheny School District Teacher Application.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 3)
    "Pittsburgh Public Schools - A Report with Options Pertaining to School Reorganization," May 10, 1974; North Allegheny School District: "Report on the Changes Inherent in the Second Draft of the Recodification Proposal" by James Manley; Report on Middle Schools by the Middle Schools Committee; Pittsburgh Council on Public Education, Statement on the 1972 Preliminary Budget of the Pittsburgh Public Schools, presented by Ruth O'Hanlon; "Pitt Middle School;" Information of SPECS: School Planning, Evaluation, and Communication System, November 6, 1974; "Pittsburgh Reorganization Plan," Pittsburgh Public Schools, January 1973; Allegheny County Schools" Program of Blue Cross Hospitalization and Blue Shield Medical-Surgical Benefits;" "The Pittsburgh Board of Education: What's Wrong with it, What Citizens Want to do about it;" Statement of Dr. Jerry C. Olson, Superintendent Pittsburgh Public Schools, on school reorganization, November 14, 1974.
- South Side (Box 3, Folder 4)
  The Birmingham Union, South Side, Pittsburgh, Restoration Projects; Outline "Topics to be Discussed on Oral History Interviews;" Pamphlet - "Since You Asked" Urban Redevelopment Authority; "Minority Contractor Bonding Program: A Manual of Organizational Steps and Procedures" and article on the same topic "Bonding Minority Contractors"; The National Center for Urban Ethnic Affairs Newsletter, October 1975; Congressional Record, October 1, 1973, introduction of Neighborhood Government Act; Obituary (Article) on Margaret Young, City Activist; Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress pamphlet, "How to Secure Additional Information About Your Subject: A Guide for Researchers to Reference Material on Their Local Communities."
- Publications (Box 3, Folder 5)
  "The Alternatives," Alternative Education Resource and Development Center; Minority News Digest, November 14, 1977; First Pittsburgh Chapter News, NOW, May 1977; The Voice of American Agri-Woman, November 1977; Coyote Howls, Autumn 1977; Daily Breakthrough: Where Women are News, November 20, 1977; Neighborhood Woman, Sept/Oct; Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, November 1977; PA NOW, November 1975, May/June 1977, January 1978; The Spokeswoman, July 15, 1974; Today's Student, October 31, 1977; Harrisburg Area Women's Newsletter, December 1976; Women in Action, June 1970, KNOW, inc.; Phi Delta Kappan, October 1973; The Whole Woman Catalog, Fall 1971; Newspaper by the Lucy Parsons Women's Coalition; Newsletter, NOW-Greater Pittsburgh Chapter, February 1970.